Guide to the Douglas Ensminger Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Douglas Ensminger papers
1951-1982
MS 1315
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
21
(21 boxes)
The papers consist of oral history transcripts, 1971-1972, covering Ensminger's years in India, 1951-1970, as representative for the Ford Foundation. The papers also include unpublished reports and memos concerning India, 1952-1982.
Ensminger, Douglas, 1910-1989
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Douglas Ensminger, 1981 and 1982.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series and one addition (Unpublished India Reports and Memos): I. Topics Related to Non-Project Areas. II. Topics Related to Specific Projects. III. Programs in Pakistan and Nepal.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of oral history transcripts, 1971-1972, covering Ensminger's years in India, 1951-1970, as representative for the Ford Foundation. The papers also include unpublished reports and memos concerning India, 1952-1982.
Childbirth -- India; Asia; India -- Economic conditions; Ensminger, Douglas, 1910-1989; Ford Foundation
- Topics Related to Non-Project Areas, Series I
  - Introduction (Box 1, Folder A1)
  - The Ford Foundation's relations with the Department of Economic Affairs, Ministry of Finance, 1971 October 19 (Box 1, Folder A2)
  - The Ford Foundation's relations with the Planning Commission, 1971 October 21 (Box 1, Folder A3)
  - Why were so many grants made to the Government of India instead of non-government agencies and institutions, 1971 October 27 (Box 1, Folder A4)
  - The delicacy of the Ford Foundation's relationships with other foreign aid giving agencies working in India, 1971 November 15 (Box 1, Folder A5)
  - The Ford Foundation's relations with the center and state government in India, 1971 November 16 (Box 1, Folder A6)
  - The Foundation's objectives and reasons for its presence in India, 1971 November 18 (Box 1, Folder A7)
  - Relationships with Nehru, 1971 November 29 (Box 1, Folder A8)
  - The significance of maintaining relations with the Cabinet, 1971 December 10 (Box 1, Folder A9)
  - The significance of relations with India's presidents, 1971 December 13 (Box 1, Folder A10)
  - Keeping in touch with all key points in India's central government power structure when advancing and discussing new ideas, 1971 December 14 (Box 1, Folder A11)
  - The importance of understanding India's foreign policy to the Foundation's operations in India (Box 1, Folder A12)
  - Need for understanding the Gandhian philosophy and different interpretations expounded by Gandhian followers, 1971 December 18 (Box 1, Folder A13)
  - Why an understanding of India's caste system was important to the Ford Foundation's working in India, 1971 December 27 (Box 1, Folder A14)
  - How were the relations defined between the Ford Foundation as an American institution working in India and the American embassy, 1972 April 18 (Box 1, Folder A15)
  - Why were there so few foreign insitutional contracts to backstop Foundation supported programs in India, 1972 April 19 (Box 1, Folder A16)
  - In what ways did the CIA issues affect the Ford Foundation's work in its relations in India, 1972 May 9 (Box 1, Folder A17)
  - What considerations went into formulating policies for housing accomodation of Foundation's foreign staff living in India, 1972 May 10 (Box 1, Folder A18)
  - The importance to the Foundation's recruitment in having the American International School, the Inter-denominational Church and the Holy Family Hospital, 1972 May 11 (Box 1, Folder A19)
  - The significance of major economic, climatic, social and political crises in India to opening the doors for major changes, 1972 May 12 (Box 1, Folder A20)
  - Importance of understanding the time and process for significant change to take place, 1972 May 23 (Box 1, Folder A21)
  - The problems involved on India's side in assigning creative people to give leadership to new and innovative programs, 1972 May 24 (Box 1, Folder A22)
  - The pros and cons of putting the maximum amount of Ford Foundation funds for India into grants in contrast to contributing to the maximum through high level staff in discussing ideas, examining alternatives and backing up India to give leadership to change and development as well as assist in starting new programs. (Where does the money go?), 1972 May 30 (Box 1, Folder A23)
  - Too much emphasis on Indian counterparts to match foreign consultants and too little concern on India's part in maximizing utilization of consultants, 1972 May 31 (Box 1, Folder A24)
  - The pros and cons of Foundation grant funds applying to both rupee and dollar costs, 1972 June 1 (Box 1, Folder A25)
  - The problems of assisting non-government organizations, agencies and institutions and the problem of these non-government institutions becoming viable, 1972 June 5 (Box 1, Folder A26)
  - Helping people locked in poverty, 1972 June 16 (Box 1, Folder A27)
  - The pros and cons of the Ford Foundation making greater use of Indians as consultants in India, 1972 June 19 (Box 1, Folder A28)
  - India's policy and practice of frequent transfer of key staff made the task of starting new programs exceedingly difficult, 1972 June 19 (Box 1, Folder A29)
  - The performance payoff of sending Indian officials abroad for short term training is marginal and of questionable value, 1972 June 19 (Box 1, Folder A30)
  - How did the Foundation function in its administrative services as it grew and functioned during the decade of the fifties and sixties, 1972 June 19 (Box 1, Folder A31)
  - The western orientation to time and quality of performance comes in the way of the working of program advisors and consultants in India, 1972 June 22 (Box 1, Folder A32)
  - The Foundation has a fetish about evaluation of projects and programs it assists with but shows little evidence of drawing on documented evidence, 1972 June 26 (Box 1, Folder A33)
  - The government of India and non-government agencies and organizations' accountability for Foundation grant funds, 1972 June 29 (Box 1, Folder A34)
  - The interaction between the Ford Foundation's India Field Office and New York office, 1972 June 30 (Box 1, Folder A35)
  - The advantages and disadvantages to the Foundation's India office in using the Institute of International Education, New York to administer fellowships, travel and study awards, and contract employees, 1972 July 6 (Box 1, Folder A36)
  - The importance of having a strategy for introducing change, 1972 October 25 (Box 1, Folder A37)
  - Recruiting Program Advisors and Consultants, 1972 October 25 (Box 1, Folder A38)
  - The "Little People" of India, 1972 November 6 (Box 1, Folder A39)
  - The Foundation's image in India, 1972 November 7 (Box 1, Folder A40)
  - The growth of the Ford Foundation's India headquarters office, 1972 November 17 (Box 2, Folder A41)
  - Recollections and reminiscences (Box 2, Folder A42)
  - The Ensminger family's experience of India (Box 2, Folder A43)
- Topics Related to Specific Projects, Series II
  - The Ford Foundation's early and continuous concern about population and family planning, 1971 November 1 (Box 3, Folder B1)
  - The Ford Foundation's contribution in the field of India's village and small industries, 1971 November 5 (Box 3, Folder B2)
  - The Foundation's persistent concern and role in assisting India achieve a status of food enough for its people, 1972 January 5 (Box 4, Folder B3)
  - The Foundation's persistent concern and role in assisting India achieve a status of food enough for its people, 1972 January 5 (Box 5, Folder B3)
  - The Foundation's persistent concern and role in assisting India achieve a status of food enough for its people, 1972 January 5 (Box 6, Folder B3)
  - The Foundation's persistent concern and role in assisting India achieve a status of food enough for its people, 1972 January 5 (Box 7, Folder B3)
  - Why did the Foundation accept and respond to Dr. B.C. Roy's invitation to assist in the development of a long range plan for the greater Calcutta area?, 1972 February 2 (Box 7, Folder B4)
  - Why did the Foundation accept and respond to Dr. B.C. Roy's invitation to assist in the development of a long range plan for the greater Calcutta area?, 1972 February 2 (Box 8, Folder B4)
  - Why did the Ford Foundation assist with India's handicrafts and handloom industry?, 1972 February 9 (Box 8, Folder B5)
  - The Ford Foundation's involvement in public administration, 1972 February 11 (Box 9, Folder B6)
  - The Ford Foundation and management education in India, 1972 March 2 (Box 9, Folder B7)
  - The historical basis of the Foundation's involvement in strengthening India's institutional competence in economics, 1972 March 29 (Box 9, Folder B8)
  - Why did the Ford Foundation get involved in training five hundred of India's young engineers in steel making, 1972 April 24 (Box 10, Folder B9)
  - The Foundation's support to the Delhi Center for the Orientation of Foreigners taking up with assignments in India, 1972 May 10 (Box 10, Folder B10)
  - The Foundation's support and withdrawal from the Center for Applied Politics, 1972 June 19 (Box 10, Folder B11)
  - The sensitivity of the Ford Foundation contributing to India's art and cultural programs, 1972 June 21 (Box 10, Folder B12)
  - India's problem of 'brain drain' and the Foundation's efforts to counteract it, 1972 June 23 (Box 10, Folder B13)
  - Ford Foundation's contribution to India in educational television and mass communications, 1972 June 23 (Box 10, Folder B14)
  - The Ford Foundation involvement and contribution in the field of law and legal education in India, 1972 June 23 (Box 10, Folder B15)
  - The Foundation's role in assisting India in its manpower, 1972 June 26 (Box 11, Folder B16)
  - The Ford Foundation's role in the field of urbanization, 1972 June 27 (Box 11, Folder B17)
  - The Ford Foundation's early interest and involvement in home economics work in India, 1972 July 5 (Box 12, Folder B18)
  - The Ford Foundation's interest and assistance in the development of the sociological sciences in India, 1972 July 10 (Box 12, Folder B19)
  - Why did the Foundation get involved in helping India make a go of nationalizing its banks?, 1972 July 11 (Box 12, Folder B20)
  - The Ford Foundation's nineteen years of involvement with India's community development program, 1972 July 11 (Box 13, Folder B21)
  - The Ford Foundation's nineteen years of involvement with India's community development program, 1972 July 11 (Box 14, Folder B21)
  - The Ford Foundation's nineteen years of involvement with India's community development program, 1972 July 11 (Box 15, Folder B21)
  - The Leigh Stevens village electricity and water project, 1972 August 21 (Box 15, Folder B22)
  - The Leigh Stevens village electricity and water project, 1972 August 21 (Box 16, Folder B22)
  - The Ford Foundation's interest and involvement in Indian education, 1972 August 23 (Box 17, Folder B23)
  - Williams College and Harvard University Public Service Fellowship program, 1972 November 6 (Box 17, Folder B24)
- Programs in Pakistan and Nepal, Series III
  - The Ford Foundation's involvement in Pakistan (1951-1953), India, and Nepal, 1972 September 22 (Box 18, Folder C1-C2)
  - The Ford Foundation's contributions to Pakistan, India, and Nepal, 1965-1972 (Box 18, Folder C2)
- Unpublished India Reports and Memos, Accession 1983-M-011
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of Accession 1983-M-011.
  - Ford Foundation Reports:
    - Marketing condoms in India, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Evaluating intensive family planning - district scheme, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Family planning publicity, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The district family planning program, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Manufacturing of male contraceptives in India, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - National Institute of Health Administration, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Evaluating community family planning, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Effects of local beliefs on attitudes toward vasectomy, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8a)
    - Report: visit to India, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8b)
    - Toward an evaluative program for intensive health and family planning, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Problems and needs of family planning, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10a)
    - Family planning information programs at the local level, undated (Box 1, Folder 10b)
    - The health and family planning programs in the state of Punjab, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11a)
    - Possible extension and modification of the family planning grant, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11b)
    - Response to questions on family planning, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12a)
    - Research needs in family planning, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12b)
    - Some observations regarding the nature and scope of action - research in family planning, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13a)
    - Extracts from "Five Year Plan for NIHAE,", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13b)
    - Interview report on fifty-six sterilization cases, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Proposal for study of intra-uterine contraceptives, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Reactions of urban employees to vasectomy operations, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Family planning program in Rajasthan, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Principles of organization and education, NIHAE, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Job specifications as a basis for training design, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19a)
    - A model for family planning action - research, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19b)
    - With loop and pill through Asia, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20a)
    - Report of a visit to Madras, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20b)
    - An experimental IUD incentive program, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21a)
    - Consultant's report, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21b)
    - In search of influence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22a)
    - Observations on population, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22b)
    - Progress in family planning in India, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 23a)
    - Role of foreign assistance in family planning, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23b)
    - Rural loop survey (missing) (Box 1, Folder 24a)
    - Interpersonal relationships of village families related to the problems of family planning, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24b)
    - Indian family planning - is failure inevitable?, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 25a)
    - Observations on family planning program and research, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25b)
    - Organization of the Central Family Planning Institute, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Television and family planning, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Major considerations in the application of satellite communication to India's family planning, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Teaching of fertility control in India and the West, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Thirteen special reports on higher education in India, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Sixteen special reports on agricultural engineering in India, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Twelve special reports on the Intensive District Agricultural Program, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Nineteen special reports on Indian agriculture, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Six special reports on community development, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Fifteen special reports on the Intensive Agricultural District Program, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Fourteen special reports on Indian administration, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Indian steel training and education program in the U.S., 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Research in area development in SIET, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - The All-India Institute for Management, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Institute for Industrial Relations, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Development of managers, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Appropriate metal working technology in India, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Industries and services for rural India, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Management research, training and consultation in India, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Agriculture and community development, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - The problems of economic development (2 copies), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Industry and communications, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Social Services, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Development of mineral resources, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 49a)
    - Irrigation and power, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 49b)
    - The National Institute of Community Development (missing) (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Administration and public co-operation (2 copies), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Village and small-scale industries, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Industry and communication (2 copies), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Trends in Indian culture in the 1970's (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Integrated rural development plan (v.1 and v.2), undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Block level planning, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Opinion leaders and communication in India, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Putting the Indian agricultural universities to work (2 copies), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - A graphical approach to settlement planning for integrated area development, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - An evaluation of the Calcutta planning and development project, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - A pilot research project in growth centers, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Agricultural mechanization in India, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Management education in India, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - A report on "Training Indian Engineers in USA for the Government of India's Steel Plants,", 1958 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Human resource - development and utilization in the 1970's (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Indian education in the 1970's (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Water use and development in India in the 1970's (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Indian politics, policy and public administration in the 1970's (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Indian agriculture in the 1970's (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Urbanization - a growing issue (2 copies), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - No rice takeover, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - The failure of the wheat trade takeover, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Agrarian reform in the Punjab, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Toward a more work-oriented schooling, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Community education and training, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Ground water comes of age, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - A charter for the land, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Water management for increasing production in the semi-arid tropics (missing) (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Water resources of India and their optimum utilization in agriculture, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Consumption patterns and preference for rice, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Agricultural progress in India, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Overcoming the obstacles to farm economic development in the less-developed countries, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - India and the 1970's (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Needed a bold new approach to development, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Frontiers of change, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Faith in the people, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Communism in India (part one), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - 220 Program letters written over the period of 19 years Dr. Ensminger was in India as the Ford Foundation representative, 1952-1970 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      General
      Missing nos. 41, 113, 138-220
      For no. 35, see Series III, Box 18 Folder C2
    - Exports in the third plan, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Policy makers, the administrators and the statisticians, undated (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Education as an investment, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Gestation logs and the rate of growth of investments, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - The National Academy of Administration, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Center-State relations (missing) (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Training in state administration in India, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Housing for the lowest incomes, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Indian Law Institute (7 articles), 1962-1967 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - India's need for well-trained lawyers, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Cooperation on problems of legal education and legal research in India, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Science policy and organization in India, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Center-State relations and the Center's food policies (missing) (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Center-State relations: West Bengal and the problems of law and order (missing) (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - The Calcutta metropolitan (missing) (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - The political situation (3 articles), 1964, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Educational television in India (4 articles), 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Educational institutions in the name of Jawaharlal Nehru, 1966 (?) (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - The Center Institute of Teaching English as a Second Language (5 articles), 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Nutrition in India -vs- USA, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - The Birla Institute of Science and Technology, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Administration and management in India (7 articles), 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Education in India (15 articles), 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Labor and industry (6 articles), 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Insuring short-term credit loans in IADP districts, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - The use of television in Indian agriculture (8 articles), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Observations on IIM, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - Report on a consultation and acquisitions trip to India and the Far East, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 116)
    - Community development and agriculture, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Kurukshetra, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Administrative policy procedures for Ford Foundation professional staff in India, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Prashashika, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Proposal to provide technical assistance to the Government of Tunisia in technology transfer, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - The progress and promise of India (2 copies), 1965 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Monthly commentary on economic conditions, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - All India Panchayat Parishad (with correspondence), 1970 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Report of discussions held with members of the Orissa government in Bhubaneshwar, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - A glimmer of light, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Youth service organization, undated (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Pamphlet list, undated (Box 4, Folder 128)